{"test_questions": [[{"question": "A pitot tube is used to measure", "opta": "pressure", "optb": "difference in pressure", "optc": "velocity of flow", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thickness of a sharp crested weir is kept less than", "opta": "one-third of the height of water on the sill", "optb": "one-half of the height of water on the sill", "optc": "one-fourth of the height of water on the sill", "optd": "two-third of the height of water on the sill", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The property of steam function \u03c8 is :", "opta": "\u03c8 is constant everwhere on any stream line", "optb": "the flow around any path in the fluid is zero for continuous flow", "optc": "the rate of change of \u03c8 with distance in an arbitrary direction, is proportional to the component of velocity normal to that direction", "optd": "the velocity vector may be found by differentiating the stream function", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum vacuum created at the summit of a syphon is", "opta": "2.7 m of water", "optb": "7.4 m of water", "optc": "5.5 m of water", "optd": "none.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the atmospheric pressure on the surface of an oil tank (sp. gr. 0.8) is 0.1 kg/cm2, the pressure at a depth of 2.5 m, is", "opta": "1 metre of water", "optb": "2 metres of water", "optc": "3 metres of water", "optd": "3.5 metres of water", "opte": "4.0 metres of water.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The total pressure force on a plane area is equal to the area multiplied by the intensity of pressure at its centroid, if", "opta": "area is horizontal", "optb": "area is vertical", "optc": "area is inclined", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the volume of a liquid weighing 3000 kg is 4 cubic metres, 0.75 is its", "opta": "specific weight", "optb": "specific mass", "optc": "specific gravity", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bernoulli's equation assumes that", "opta": "fluid is non-viscous", "optb": "fluid is homogeneous", "optc": "flow is steady", "optd": "flow is along the stream line", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The time required to close a valve gradually is (where L is the length of pipe and C = velocity of pressure wave)", "opta": "", "optb": "\u2264", "optc": ">", "optd": "<", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A syphon is used", "opta": "to connect water reservoirs at different levels intervened by a hill", "optb": "to supply water to a town from higher level to lower level", "optc": "to fill up a tank with water at higher level from a lower level", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most economical section of a circular channel for maximum discharge", "opta": "depth of water = 0.95 diameter of circular section", "optb": "hydraulic mean depth = 0.286 diameter of circular section", "optc": "wetted perimeter = 2.6 diameter of circular section", "optd": "wetted perimeter = 2.83 depth of water", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Unit of kinematic viscosity is", "opta": "m2/sec", "optb": "Newton sec/m2", "optc": "Newton sec/m3", "optd": "Kg sec/m2.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The moment of inertia of a floating body along its longitudinal axis and the volume of water displaced by it are I and V respectively. The height of the metacentre above centre of buoyancy of the body, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Time of emptying liquid from a hemispherical vessel through an orifice at its bottom, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Critical depth (h) of a channel, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of maximum velocity to average velocity of viscous fluid through a circular pipe is", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "0.75", "optc": "1.25", "optd": "2.00", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The shear stress distribution in viscous fluid through a circular pipe is :", "opta": "maximum at the centre", "optb": "maximum at the inside of surface", "optc": "same throughout the section", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Product of Renold number, Froud's number and Mach number is :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "For tranquil flow h > 2g or v <", "optb": "For critical flow", "optc": "For torrential flow h >  or v < gh", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The side slope of Cipolletti weir is generally kept", "opta": "1 to 4", "optb": "1 to 3", "optc": "1 to 2", "optd": "1 : 5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A cylinder 3 m in diameter and 4 m long retains water one side as shown in the below figure. If the weight of the cylinder is 2000 kgf, the horizontal reaction at B is", "opta": "10,000 kgf", "optb": "15,000 kgf", "optc": "20,000 kgf", "optd": "18,000 kgf.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Inside pressure in a hollow soap bubble in the air is : (where d is the diameter of the bubble)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The momentum correction factor (\u03b2) for the viscous flow through a circular pipe is", "opta": "1.25", "optb": "1.33", "optc": "1.50", "optd": "1.66", "opte": "2.00", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A piezometer opening in pipes measures", "opta": "velocity head", "optb": "static pressure", "optc": "total pressure", "optd": "negative static pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An independent mass of a fluid does not posses", "opta": "elevation energy", "optb": "kinetic energy", "optc": "pressure energy", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While applying the Bernoulli's equation  = total head, the work any section done on the flow system, if any", "opta": "is added on the right side of the equation", "optb": "is added on the left side of the equation", "optc": "is ignored", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge Q over a rectangular weir of length L and height H, is given by the equation", "opta": "Q = 2/3 Cd2g LH3/2", "optb": "Q = 2/3 CdL H2gH", "optc": "", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A short tube mouthpiece will not run full at its outlet if the head under which the orifice works, is", "opta": "less than 12.2 m of the water", "optb": "more than 12.2 m of the water", "optc": "equal of 12.2 m of water", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrostatic pressure on a dam depends upon its", "opta": "length", "optb": "depth", "optc": "shape", "optd": "material", "opte": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When two layers of a fluid separated by dy move over the other with a difference of velocity dv, causes a shearing stress , where \u03bc is known as", "opta": "coefficient of viscosity", "optb": "absolute viscosity", "optc": "dynamic viscosity", "optd": "viscosity", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pipe of 0.1 m2 cross sectional area suddenly enlarges to 0.3 m2 cross-sectional area. If the discharge of the pipe is 0.3 m3 /sec, the head loss is", "opta": "2/g m of water", "optb": "g/2 m of water", "optc": "1g m of water", "optd": "g m of water.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum efficiency of transmission of power through a pipe, is", "opta": "25%", "optb": "33.3%", "optc": "50%", "optd": "66.67%.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An ideal flow of a liquid obeys", "opta": "Continuity equation", "optb": "Newton's law of viscosity", "optc": "Newton's second law of motion", "optd": "dynamic viscosity law,", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Euler's equation for motion of liquids, is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "\u03c1dp + gdz + vdv = 0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reynold number is the ratio of initial force and", "opta": "viscosity", "optb": "elasticity", "optc": "gravitational force", "optd": "surface tension.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When a body is totally or partially immersed in a fluid, it is buoyed up by a force equal to", "opta": "weight of the body", "optb": "weight of the fluid displaced by the body", "optc": "weight of the body and fluild displaced by the body", "optd": "difference of weights of the fluid displaced and that of the body", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If D is the diameter of a pipe of length L and f is the coefficient of friction of pipe then diameter of the nozzle d is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the total head of the nozzle of a pipe is 37.5 m and discharge is 1 cumec, the power generated is", "opta": "400 H.P.", "optb": "450 H.P.", "optc": "500 H.P.", "optd": "550 H.P.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The phenomenon occuring in an open channel when a rapidly flowing stream abruptly changes to a slowly flowing stream causing a distinct rise of liquid surface, is", "opta": "water hammer", "optb": "hydraulic jump", "optc": "critical discharge", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a circular pipe of length L and diameter d, a viscous liquid is flowing with a velocity v. The loss in head, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The horizontal component of the force on a curved surface is equal to", "opta": "weight of liquid vertically below the curved surface", "optb": "force on a vetical projection of the curved surface", "optc": "product of pressure at its centroid and the area", "optd": "weight of liquid retained by the curved area.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The radius of gyration of the water line of a floating ship is 4 m and its metacentric height is 72.5 cm. The period of oscillation of the ship, is", "opta": "\u03c0", "optb": "2\u03c0", "optc": "3\u03c0", "optd": "4\u03c0", "opte": "\u03c0/2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A pipe consisting of several pipes of varying diameters and lengths, may be replaced by an equivalent pipe of diameter D of length", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Empirical formula  for discharge over large rectangular weirs, is known as", "opta": "Francis formula", "optb": "Bazin formula", "optc": "Rehbook formula", "optd": "Kutter's formula.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diameter (d) of a nozzle fixed at the end of a pipe (diameter D, length L) for maximum energy, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement regarding Borda's mouth piece running full from the following :", "opta": "Actual velocity at the out let is gH", "optb": "Theoretical velocity at the outlet is 2gH", "optc": "Coefficient of velocity is 1/2", "optd": "Coefficient of contraction is 1", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Differential manometers are used to measure", "opta": "pressure in water channels, pipes, etc.", "optb": "difference in pressure at two points", "optc": "atmospheric pressure", "optd": "very low pressure.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A tank 4m x 3m x 2m containing an oil of specific gravity 0.83 is moved with an acceleration g/2 m sec2. The ratio of the pressures at its bottom when it is moving vertically up and down, is", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "1/2", "optd": "1/3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most familiar form of Bernoulli's equation, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "= constant head", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Highest dam in India, is", "opta": "Bhakra dam", "optb": "Hirakund dam", "optc": "Nagarjuna Sagar dam", "optd": "Iddiki dam.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}